[Music]
Reedman reads
The Giver by Lois Lowry, narrated by Fraser Reedman.
Chapter 20.
[Music]
"I won't! I won't go home!. You can't make me!". Jonas sobbed and shouted and pounded
the bed with his fists..
""Sit up,, Jonas,"." The Giver told him firmly..
Jonas obeyed him.. Weeping,, shuddering,, he sat on the edge of the bed.. He would
not look at The Giver.. ""You may stay here tonight.. I want to talk to you., But
you must be quiet now, while I notify your family unit..
No one must hear you cry.". Jonas looked up wildly.. "No one heard that little twin
cry, either!. No one but my father!". He collapsed in sobs again.. The Giver
waited silently.. Finally, Jonas was able to quiet himself and he sat huddled,, his
shoulders shaking.. The Giver went to the wall speaker and clicked the switch to ON..
"Yes,, Receiver.. How may I help you?"?
"Notify the new receivers's family unit that he will be staying with me tonight,.
for additional training.".
"I will take care of that,, sir.. Thank you for your instructions,",
the voice said.. "I will take care of that,, sir.. I will take care of that,,
sir,". Jonas mimicked in a cruel,, sarcastic voice.. "I will do whatever you
like,, sir.. I will kill people,, sir.. Old people?, Small newborn people?, I'd be
happy to kill them,, sir.. Thank you for your instructions,, sir.. How may I help
you? He couldn't seem to stop.. The Giver grasped his shoulders firmly.. Jonas fell
silent and stared at him.. "Listen to me,, Jonas.. They can't help it.. They know
nothing.. "You said that to me before.". "I said that because it's true.. It's the
way they live.. It's the life that was created for them.. It's the same life
that you would have, if you had not been chosen as my successor.". "But he lied to
me!". Jonas wept.. "It's what he was told to do,, and he knows nothing else.". "What
about you?? Do you lie to me,, too?"? Jonas almost spat the question at The Giver.. "I
am empowered to lie., But I've never lied to you.". Jonas stared at him.. "Release is
always like that?. For people who break the rules three times? For the Old?. Do
they kill the Old,, too?"? "Yes,, it's true.
what about Fiona?? She loves the Old!.
She's in training to care for them.. Does she know yet?? What will she do when she
finds out?? How will she feel?"? Jonas brushed wetness from his face with the
back of one hand.. "Fiona is already being trained in the fine art of release,". The
Giver told him., ""She's very efficient at her work,, your red-haired friend..
Feelings are not part of the life she's learned."." Jonas wrapped his arms around
himself and rocked his own body back and forth.. ""What should I do?? I can't go
back!. I can't!"." The Giver stood up..
""First,, I will order our evening meal., Then we will eat."." Jonas found himself
using the nasty,, sarcastic voice again..
"Then we'll have a sharing of feelings?".
The Giver gave a rofful, anguished,, empty laugh.. "Jonas,, you and I are the
only ones who have feelings.. We've been sharing them now for almost a year.". "I'm
sorry,, Giver,", Jonas said miserably.. "I don't mean to be so hateful.. Not to you.".
The Giver rubbed Jonas's hunched shoulders.. "And after we eat,", he went on,.
"we'll make a plan.". Jonas looked up,, puzzled.. "A plan for what?? There's
nothing.. There's nothing we could do..
It's always been this way.. Before me,, before you,? before the ones who came
before you.. Back and back and back.". His voice trailed the familiar phrase..
"Jonas,", The Giver said, after a moment,.
"it's true that it has been this way for what seems forever., But the memories
tell us that it has not always been..
People felt things once.. You and I have been part of that,. so, we know.. We know
that they once felt things like pride, and sorrow, and—" "And love,", Jonas added,,
remembering the family scene that had so affected him.. "And pain.", He thought again
of the soldier.. "The worst part of holding the memories is not the pain.,
It's the loneliness of it.. Memories need to be shared.". "I've started to share them
with you, Jonah said,, trying to cheer him.. "That's true.. And having you here
with me over the past year has made me realize that things must change.. For
years I felt that they should,, but it seemed so hopeless.. "Now for the first
time. I think there might be a way,", The Giver said slowly.. "And you brought it to
my attention, barely—". He glanced at the clock,. "two hours ago.", Jonas watched him,
and listened.. It was late at night, now..
They had talked and talked.. Jonas sat wrapped in a robe belonging to The
Giver,. the long robe that only Elders wore.. It was possible, what they had planned..
Barely possible.. If it failed,, he would very likely be killed.. But what did that
matter?? If he stayed,, his life was no longer worth living.. "Yes,", he told The
Giver.. "I'll do it.. I think I can do it..
I'll try, anyway., But I want you to come with me.". The Giver shook his head..
"Jonas,", he said,, ""the community has depended, all these generations, back and
back and back, on a resident Receiver to hold their memories for them.. I've
turned over many of them to you in the past year.. And I can't take them back..
There's no way for me to get them back if I have given them.. "So if you escape,
once you're gone— —and, Jonas,, you know that you can never return—"." Jonas nodded
solemnly.. It was the terrifying part..
"Yes,", he said,, ""I know., But if you come with me—"," The Giver shook his head, made
a gesture to silence him.. He continued., ""If you get away, you get beyond,, if you
get to Elsewhere,, it will mean that the community has to bear the burden
themselves, of the memories you had been holding for them.. "I think that they can,
and that they will acquire some wisdom., But it will be desperately hard for
them.." When we lost Rosemary 10 years ago, and her memories returned to the
people,, they panicked.. And those were such few memories, compared to yours..
When your memories return, they all need help.. Remember how I helped you in the
beginning, when the receiving of memories was new to you?"? Jonas nodded.. "It was
scary at first., And it hurt a lot.". "You needed me then., And now they will.". "It's
no use. They'll find someone to take my place.. They'll choose a new Receiver.".
"There's no one ready for training,. not right away.. Oh,, they'll speed up the
selection,, of course., But I can't think of another child who has the right
qualities—". "There's a little female with pale eyes. she's only a Six.". "That's
correct.. I know the one you mean.. Her name is Catherine. But she's too young..
So, they will be forced to bear those memories.". "I want you to come,, Giver,",
Jonas pleaded.. "No., I have to stay here,", The Giver said firmly.. "I want to,, Jonas..
If I go with you, and together we take all their protection from the memories,.
Jonas,, the community will be left with no one to help them.. They'll be thrown
into chaos.. They'll destroy themselves..
I can't go. GG, Jonas suggested,. "you and I don't need to care about the rest of
them.". The Giver looked at him with a questioning smile.. Jonas hung his head..
Of course, they needed to care.. It was the meaning of everything.. "And in any
case,, Jonas,", The Giver sighed,, "I wouldn't make it.. I'm very weakened now..
Do you know that I no longer see colors?"?
Jonas's heart broke.. He reached for The givers's hand.. "You have the colors,", The
Giver told him.. "And you have the courage.. I will help you to have the
strength.". "A year ago,", Jonas reminded him,. "when I had just become a 12, when I
began to see the first color,, you told me that the beginning had been different
for you., But that I wouldn't understand.".
The Giver brightened.. "That's true.. And do you know,, Jonas, with all your
knowledge now,, with all your memories,, with all you've learned—, still you won't
understand? Because I've been a little selfish.. I haven't given any of it to
you.. I wanted to keep it for myself to the last.". "Keep what?
Now, I was just a boy,, younger than you,.
it began to come to me., But it wasn't the seeing beyond for me.. It was
different. For me,. it was hearing -beyond.".
Jonas frowned,, trying to figure that out.. ""What did you hear?"?" he asked..
""Music,"," The Giver said,, smiling.. ""I began to hear something truly
remarkable,, and it's called music.. I'll give you some before I go."."
Jonas shook his head emphatically.. ""No, give her," he said.. ""I want you to keep
that, to have with you, when I'm gone."."
Jonas went home the next morning,, cheerfully greeted his parents,, and lied
easily about what a busy,, pleasant night he had had.. His father smiled and lied
easily,, too,, about his busy and pleasant day the day before.. Throughout the
school day,, as he did his lessons,, Jonas went over the plan in his head.. It
seemed startlingly simple..
Jonas and The Giver had gone over it and over it, late into the night hours.. For
the next two weeks,, as the time for the December Ceremony approached,, The Giver
would transfer every memory of courage and strength that he could to Jonas.. He
would need those to help him find the Elsewhere that they were both sure
existed.. They knew it would be a very difficult journey.. Then,, in the middle
of the night before the Ceremony,, Jonas would secretly leave his dwelling.. This
was probably the most dangerous part yet, because it was a violation of a
major rule for any citizen not on official business to leave a dwelling at
night.. "I'll leave at midnight, Jonah said.. "The Food Collectors will be
finished picking up the evening meal remains by then,, and the path
maintenance Crews don't start their work that early. there won't be anyone to see
me,, unless of course someone's out on emergency business.". "I don't know what
you should do if you are seen,, Jonas,", The Giver had said.. "I have memories,, of
course,, of all kinds of escapes., People fleeing from terrible things throughout
history., But every situation is individual. There's no memory of one
like this.". "I'll be careful, Jonah said..
"No one will see me.". "As receiver in training, you're held in very high
respect already., So I think you wouldn't be questioned very forcefully. I just
say I was on some important errand for the Receiver.. I'd say it was all your
fault that I was out after hours,". Jonas teased.. They both laughed a little
nervously.. But Jonas was certain that he could slip away, unseen, from his house,,
carrying an extra set of clothing..
Silently, he would take his bicycle to the riverbank and leave it there, hidden
in the bushes with the clothing folded beside it.. Then he would make his way
through the darkness, on foot, silently, to the Annex.. ""There's no nighttime
attendant,"," The Giver explained.. ""I'll leave the door unlocked.. You simply slip
into the room.. I'll be waiting for you."."
His parents would discover, when they awoke that he was gone.. They would also
find a cheerful note from Jonas on his bed, telling them that he was going for
an early morning ride along the river;, that he would be back for the Ceremony..
His parents would be irritated, but not alarmed.. They would think him
inconsiderate, and they would plan to chastise him, later.. They would wait, with
mounting anger, for him;. finally, they would be forced to go,, taking Lily to
the Ceremony without him.. "They won't say anything to anyone,, though,", Jonas said,
quite certain.. "They won't call attention to my rudeness because it would reflect
on their parenting.. And anyway, everyone's so involved in the Ceremony
that they probably won't notice that I'm not there.. Now that I'm a 12 and in
training,, I don't have to sit with my age group anymore. So Asher will think
I'm with my parents, or with you—", "And your parents will assume you're with
Asher, or with me. Jonah shrugged.. "It will take everyone a while to realize
that I'm not there at all.". "And you and I
will be long on our way by then.". In the early morning,, The Giver would order a
vehicle and driver from the Speaker.. He visited the other communities
frequently,, meeting with their Elders;.
his responsibilities extended over all the surrounding areas., So this would not
be an unusual undertaking.. Ordinarily, The Giver did not attend a December
Ceremony.. Last year, he had been present because of the occasion of Jonas's
selection,, in which he was so involved., But his life was usually quite separate
from that of the community.. No one would comment on his absence, or on the fact
that he had chosen to stay to be away..
When the driver and vehicle arrived,, The Giver would send the driver on some
brief errand.. During his absence,, The Giver would help Jonas hide in the
storage area of the vehicle.. He would have with him a bundle of food, which
The Giver would save from his own meals.
during the next two weeks, Ceremony would begin, with all the community
there. by then, Jonas and The Giver would be on their way.. By midday,
Jonas's absence would become apparent, and would be a cause for serious
concern.. The Ceremony would not be disrupted—. —such a disruption would be
unthinkable., But searchers would be sent out into the community.. By the time his
bicycle and clothing were found,, The Giver would be returning.. Jonas,, by
then,, would be on his own,, making his journey Elsewhere.. The Giver,, on his
return,, would find the community in a state of confusion and panic..
Confronted by a situation which they had never faced before,, and having no
memories from which to find either solace or wisdom,, they would not know
what to do, and would seek his advice..
He would go to the Auditorium, where the people would be gathered, still.. He would
stride to the stage and command their attention.. He would make the solemn
announcement that Jonas had been lost in the river.. He would immediately begin
the Ceremony of Loss.. "Jonas,. Jonas,". they would say loudly, as they had once said
the name of Caleb.. The Giver would lead the chant.. Together they would let
Jonas's presence in their lives fade away as they said his name in unison
more slowly,, softer and softer, until he was disappearing from them, until he was
no more than an occasional murmur. and then, by the end of the long day,, gone
forever,, not to be mentioned again..
Their attention would turn to the overwhelming task of bearing the
memories themselves.. The Giver would help them.. "Yes,, I understand that
they'll need you,"," Jonas had said at the end of the lengthy discussion and
planning., ""But I'll need you,, too..
Please come with me."," He knew the answer, even as he made the final plea..
""My work will be finished,"," The Giver had replied gently. "And I have helped
the community to change and become whole.. "I'm grateful to you,, Jonas,,
because without you, I would never have figured out a way to bring about the change..
But your role now is to escape. And my role is to stay.". "But don't you want to
be with me,, Giver?"? Jonas asked sadly..
The Giver hugged him.. "I love you,, Jonas,", he said. I have another place to go..
When my work here is finished,, I want to be with my daughter.". Jonas had been
staring glumbly at the floor.. Now he looked up,, startled.. "I didn't know you
had a daughter,, Giver!. You told me that you had a spouse. I never knew about
your daughter.". The Giver smiled, and nodded.. For the first time in their long
months together, Jonah saw him look truly happy..
"Her name was Rosemary,", The Giver said.
[Music]